<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title><![CDATA[Development notes by Yaroslav Yermilov]]></title><link href="https://yermilov.github.io/categories/static-sites/atom.xml" rel="self"/><link href="https://yermilov.github.io/"/><updated>2018-01-13T23:36:41+00:00</updated><id>https://yermilov.github.io/</id><author><name><![CDATA[Yaroslav Yermilov]]></name></author><generator uri="http://sysgears.com/grain/">Grain</generator><entry><title type="html"><![CDATA[Groovy static sites with Grain]]></title><link href="https://yermilov.github.io/blog/2017/06/27/groovy-static-sites-with-grain/"/><updated>2017-06-27T01:04:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/06/27/groovy-static-sites-with-grain/</id><content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>The first option I considered when I decided to start up this blog was to use static site generator, and Jekyll as the most popular one was an obvious choice.
Shortly after I was ready with the first version of this blog and first post - <a href="/blog/2017/02/20/using-jekyll-asciidoctor-and-github-pages-for-static-site-creation/" target="_blank">Using Jekyll, Asciidoctor and GitHub Pages for static site creation</a>, I&#8217;ve noticed a link in <a href="https://twitter.com/sdelamo" target="_blank">@sdelamo</a> <a href="http://groovycalamari.com/issues/68" target="_blank">Groovy Calamary #68</a> to the static site generator from Groovy world - <a href="https://sysgears.com/grain/" target="_blank">Grain</a>.
As I consider myself as a Groovy ecosystem fan, I could not resist it and quickly migrated this blog to Grain.</p>
</div>
<!--more-->
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_service_site_generators">Service site generators</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Typical web resource after you request a page from it does something like following:</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p>fetch some data from storage</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>process it</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>select one of web page templates and render it</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>return result</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Many of them do not require dedicated data storage or data itself is changing relatively rarely.
It means that web pages can be generated once and served without no additional processing for every request.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It&#8217;s important that we should not return to the boring Web 1.0 world.
If client state on your site is not persisted, it can be handled by JavaScript locally.
If the content is changing relatively rarely, you can just redeploy it with every change.
If you need something like commenting feature, you can rely on external resources (for example <a href="https://disqus.com" target="_blank">disqus.com</a> in this case).</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And if you get rid of all heavy dynamic weapons like databases and server-side code and express your site as a collection of HMTL, CSS and JavaScript files you can gain some good benefits: ease of site deployment, content caching and delivering (which leads to better performance) and security management.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Typical static site generator takes your content (it can be plain text file, markdown, asciidoc, etc.) along with bunch of configuration parameters and the desired layout (usually HTML with some kind of template DSL) and transform them into a collection of HTML, CSS and JavaScript files ready for deployment and servicing as a static web resource.
According to <a href="https://www.staticgen.com/" target="_blank">staticgen.com</a>, there are dozens of different static sites generators, and <a href="https://jekyllrb.com" target="_blank">Jekyll</a> is the most popular from them.
I&#8217;ve already posted an <a href="/blog/2017/02/20/using-jekyll-asciidoctor-and-github-pages-for-static-site-creation/" target="_blank">article</a> about Jekyll, and today we will look closely at <a href="https://sysgears.com/grain/" target="_blank">Grain</a>, which is a workhorse of this blog itself.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_so_grain">So, Grain</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Grain is an open source static website generator for Groovy.
It provides all usual static site generator features and moreover has a particular killer feature - Groovy is a privileged citizen for all kinds of source files (configuration, layout, content and more).</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Starting Grain blog is as easy as downloading one of its <a href="https://sysgears.com/grain/themes/" target="_blank">themes</a>.
Let&#8217;s examine it with yet another blog example, which means <a href="https://sysgears.com/grain/themes/octopress/" target="_blank">Grain Octopress Theme</a> is theme of our choice.
To ensure everything is working open your project directory and execute following:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist8287efd2bfe42acdd125578282e0ab2f">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/8287efd2bfe42acdd125578282e0ab2f.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If you open now <a href="http://localhost:4000" target="_blank">http://localhost:4000</a>, you should see following:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/3600d-3600d28dd51938ac3d3da7ec351d3114.png" alt="3600d 3600d28dd51938ac3d3da7ec351d3114">
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_now_some_housekeeping">Now some housekeeping</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Before start using Grain, you need to perform some housekeeping.
For example, as Grain try to rely on Groovy ecosystem tool as much as possible, it uses Gradle as build tool.
But distribution that we&#8217;ve just download uses version 1.8 of Gradle wrapper (for the moment of writing this article 4.0 is actual version).
You can easily update it by applying following change to <em>build.gradle</em> file:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistad77d1f1c747791a37491d7cdaf6125c">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/ad77d1f1c747791a37491d7cdaf6125c.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And running following command:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistd44849eee1050307969f218b29a7b869">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/d44849eee1050307969f218b29a7b869.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Also, it would be great to update <em>.gitignore</em> file to ignore irrelevant for VCS files as following:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist67f0c7aae6a9299f3d58c15415078f21">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/67f0c7aae6a9299f3d58c15415078f21.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You should also fix JVM memory configuration in <em>grainw</em> files:</p>
</div>


<div id="gista27c146412d4d6abcbde9331d312c9af">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/a27c146412d4d6abcbde9331d312c9af.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Modern web requires you to serve all your site content over HTTPS protocol.
By default, not all Grain Octopress Theme content complies it.
You should edit file <em>theme/includes/custom/head.html</em> as following:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist365b888e528ddeca13604ac1a492df87">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/365b888e528ddeca13604ac1a492df87.js"></script>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_adding_new_post">Adding new post</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The first thing you probably want to do with your blog is to create a new post.
To do it, add file named <em>yyyy-mm-dd-new-post.adoc</em> (substitute yyyy-mm-dd with publication date and new-post with short post name) with following content:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist57ddf7f0300c32ccc937783f565d2b9b">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/57ddf7f0300c32ccc937783f565d2b9b.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As you can see, another great thing about Grain is that it supports <a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/" target="_blank">Asciidoc</a> format out-of-the-box.
It&#8217;s a great benefit if your blog is going to be developer-oriented, and you probably may be satisfied with using neither markdown nor HTML for your posts.
Asciidoc shares the same concept as <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/" target="_blank">Markdown</a>, is partially compatible with it but has much more powerful features needed for advanced drafting of articles, technical manuals, books, presentations, and prose.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now your blog should look like following:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/8020f-8020f393565a558551c6c2e341b84c45.png" alt="8020f 8020f393565a558551c6c2e341b84c45">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And if you follow new post link:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/cf787-cf787cc6e036ab60a8b546f9d25019e8.png" alt="cf787 cf787cc6e036ab60a8b546f9d25019e8">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As I said in the beginning, Groovy is a privileged citizen in the Grain world.
To prove it, in the following sections I will demonstrate simple examples how you can use Groovy in all kinds of site sources - configuration, layout, content and even deployment.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_site_configuration">Site configuration</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As you can see, there are plenty of defaults used by your blog now.
This problem is easily fixed via <em>SiteConfig.groovy</em> file.
What is important, is that it is implemented as executable Groovy script, which constructs site build context.
Inside it you can:</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>assign primitive values to configuration parameters</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>


<div id="gistdf26ecc1e8cf0635e4e9eba6d94c0b86">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/df26ecc1e8cf0635e4e9eba6d94c0b86.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>use special Groovy literals like patterns, string templates or lists</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>


<div id="gist1aa616b0e89a9c1c858e6d96bb94f0c6">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/1aa616b0e89a9c1c858e6d96bb94f0c6.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>instantiate objects and execute methods on them</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>


<div id="gist9763624cf6becc9be3b5afce43b073fd">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/9763624cf6becc9be3b5afce43b073fd.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>use Groovy builders for hierarchical parameters</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>


<div id="gist6d4ceea06cb9ab146ad5ed1191216a82">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/6d4ceea06cb9ab146ad5ed1191216a82.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You can find tons of parameters there and even introduce your own.
For the beginning, let&#8217;s concentrate on the simple ones and perform following changes:</p>
</div>


<div id="giste36aa454a84fa42563ae9cf9689abc8d">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/e36aa454a84fa42563ae9cf9689abc8d.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now, your blog should look a little bit more personal:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/0cc17-0cc176f669122a794295dfaf7aca36bc.png" alt="0cc17 0cc176f669122a794295dfaf7aca36bc">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Moreover, you can use <code>commands</code> object to create custom commands for grain cli.</p>
</div>


<div id="gist83914dd6bc422569d7ecb9ef21ebfb30">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/83914dd6bc422569d7ecb9ef21ebfb30.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It means that if you execute <code>./grainw create-post 'HOWTO: create post from CLI'</code> you will got following result:</p>
</div>


<div id="gista1d47cfc42df32c2294bfd6392bf3b00">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/a1d47cfc42df32c2294bfd6392bf3b00.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/ee478-ee4782118817e6e1cf4c09b17cd8cab8.png" alt="ee478 ee4782118817e6e1cf4c09b17cd8cab8">
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_site_layout">Site layout</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Grain has a pretty usual layout system.
Let&#8217;s explore it using example of <em>theme/layouts/blog.html</em> which controls layout of site home page.</p>
</div>


<div id="gistd31cd182f6ebd74926fae55e4fb4e0ac">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/d31cd182f6ebd74926fae55e4fb4e0ac.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>On the lines 1-5, you can see typical page front matter.
First of all, it configures layout inheritance.
You can open file named <em>theme/layouts/default.html</em>, which is parent layout for <em>blog.html</em> and check that  <em>blog.html</em> content will be put inside <code>${content}</code> tag (line 14) of <em>default.html</em>:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist472a52e4be5bbfab967715a2d8d90cca">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/472a52e4be5bbfab967715a2d8d90cca.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Following lines of front matter are passed into special <code>page</code> object and can be used to parametrize layout behavior.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>After front matter, we see kind of normal HTML code with addition of Groovy.
It can be one-liner, just like in lines 19 and 36.
In these concrete example special implicit method <code>include</code> is used, which takes another HTML file and optionally parameters map, renders their content and insert into original page.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The more sophisticated option is multi-line Groovy code, which is, however, very natural and clear.
You can use <code>if</code> statement (like in line 8) to control which parts of page layout should be rendered and which not.
As a result, you do not need any special constructions as many other static site generators have.
For example, if you require rendering collection of elements, you can use Groovy Collection API like in line 16.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>With such approach you can quickly implement some interesting features like in line 17, where you loop through list of blog posts, render content of each one, extract briefs and put them on your home page.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_site_content">Site content</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Just like with layout files you can simply put any Groovy code anywhere in your content file.
For example, if you modify latest generated post as following:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist42639e6e2d6157fc54c71314a5bcfd98">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/42639e6e2d6157fc54c71314a5bcfd98.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You will get something like:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/05279-05279b8895a2b4ce8c0efb67f7a9f307.png" alt="05279 05279b8895a2b4ce8c0efb67f7a9f307">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Pay attention that this code will be executed once and its result will be put into static HTML page.
If you need dynamic behavior you will probable need something like:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistac9904062cbeb91196034b423e4c1247">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/ac9904062cbeb91196034b423e4c1247.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If you need to reuse some code in multiple places, there is an excellent feature called custom tags in Grain.
If you have an experience with template frameworks like JSP, you can find something familiar in it.
As reference, open file <em>\theme\src\com\sysgears\octopress\taglibs\OctopressTagLib.groovy</em> which already contains several very useful tags like <code>gist</code> or <code>img</code>.
As you can see, custom tag is as simple as Groovy closure and HTML template so that we can implement our own in 3 minutes.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>First, add following closure to <em>\theme\src\com\sysgears\octopress\taglibs\OctopressTagLib.groovy</em>:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist4abbf385d08118452dd25162ca42986e">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/4abbf385d08118452dd25162ca42986e.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Then, create new file <em>\theme\includes\tags\dateNow.html</em> with following content:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistf799a454c3be0d07fc44cced4f41c0be">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/f799a454c3be0d07fc44cced4f41c0be.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And last, modify your content page:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistc7e583fa6da4ca837114094ba408f73a">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/c7e583fa6da4ca837114094ba408f73a.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Ready! You will get something like:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/22b63-77df0a95716854e6fd110dd4d29c2a14.png" alt="22b63 77df0a95716854e6fd110dd4d29c2a14">
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_deployment_to_github_pages">Deployment to GitHub Pages</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now, it&#8217;s time to finalize all our efforts and publish results of our work to the internet.
It can be achieved easily with support of <a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages</a> - web platform that serves static content from GitHub repositories.
If you put some static resources to your repository branch named <em>gh-pages</em>, GitHub Pages will automatically serve it as web resource.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So, first obvious option is to run <code>./grainw generate</code> and push content of <em>dist</em> folder to the <em>gh-pages</em> branch of your repository manually. But it is so boring!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Let&#8217;s rather set up automatic pipeline: <a href="https://travis-ci.org/" target="_blank">Travis CI job</a> which will be started automatically by each commit to <em>develop</em> branch, and actually do the same: run <code>./grainw generate</code> and push content of <em>dist</em> folder to the <em>gh-pages</em> branch from the same repository.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The first thing we need to do - generate key pair, so Travis job will have permissions to push to your repository. To achieve it just run <code>ssh-keygen -t rsa</code> in your shell.
Then, go to <a href="https://github.com/settings/keys" target="_blank">GitHub settings page</a>, and register new SSH key by providing its public part.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Next, create file <em>.travis.yml</em> to configure Travis job with following content:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist06601cf711422ecc791d3cd85c5cc3c0">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/06601cf711422ecc791d3cd85c5cc3c0.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Don&#8217;t forget to enable your repository build at <a href="https://travis-ci.org/profile/" target="_blank">Travis dashboard</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As you can see, Travis is supposed to take private part of your generated key from <em>.travis/</em> directory.
But surely it&#8217;s not safe to put something private into public GitHub repository.
Luckily enough, Travis supports file encryption.
All you need is to run <code>travis encrypt-file .travis/id_rsa --add</code>.
But it&#8217;s important to know two tweaks regarding this command: first, be careful enough to commit encrypted file <em>id_rsa.enc</em> instead of original <em>.travis/id_rsa</em> and second - this command does not work on Windows boxes, you need a *nix one.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As you can see, there is almost no manual scripting for interaction with git in job definition.
The reason is that grain has special <code>grainw deploy</code> command which will invoke <em>\theme\src\com\sysgears\octopress\deploy\GHPagesDeployer.groovy</em> script.
It works fine with manual deployment process but needs some improvements to integrate with Travis.
You can take desired code here:</p>
</div>


<div id="gisted573c2c93e1ed69d6a9c552a7cf8898">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/ed573c2c93e1ed69d6a9c552a7cf8898.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><em>GHPagesDeployer</em> script is instantiated in <em>SiteConfig</em> script we already seen.
You need to configure it, by providing single parameter inside <em>SiteConfig.groovy</em> file:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistf5f2d9d09a9f52a842e25517f963be01">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/f5f2d9d09a9f52a842e25517f963be01.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The last thing you should do is to go to the setting of your Travis job and enable <em>Build only if .travis.yml is present</em> to prevent Travis from running build for <em>gh-pages</em> branch.
Now you can push your latest changes to GitHub and watch how they will be processed by Travis job.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-06-27-groovy-static-sites-with-grain/19ae2-19ae2566e5deb30c71da1348d45182f1.png" alt="19ae2 19ae2566e5deb30c71da1348d45182f1">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If you&#8217;ve done everything correctly, you should get the same result as I have here - <a href="https://yermilov.github.io/grain-example/" target="_blank">https://yermilov.github.io/grain-example</a> (sources can be examined <a href="https://github.com/yermilov/grain-example" target="_blank">here</a>).</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_links">Links</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://www.staticgen.com/" target="_blank">Top Open-Source Static Site Generators</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://jekyllrb.com" target="_blank">Jekyll&#8217;s home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="/blog/2017/02/20/using-jekyll-asciidoctor-and-github-pages-for-static-site-creation/" target="_blank">Using Jekyll, Asciidoctor and GitHub Pages for static site creation</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://sysgears.com/grain/" target="_blank">Grain&#8217;s home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://github.com/yermilov/grain-example" target="_blank">Sample repository</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/" target="_blank">Markdown home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org" target="_blank">Asciidoctor home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/" target="_blank">What is Asciidoc?</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-writers-guide/" target="_blank">Asciidoc Writer&#8217;s Guide</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-syntax-quick-reference/" target="_blank">Asciidoc Syntax Quick Reference</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/user-manual/" target="_blank">Asciidoctor User Manual</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://travis-ci.org/" target="_blank">Travis CI</a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Jekyll, Asciidoctor and GitHub Pages for static site creation]]></title><link href="https://yermilov.github.io/blog/2017/02/20/using-jekyll-asciidoctor-and-github-pages-for-static-site-creation/"/><updated>2017-02-20T02:27:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/02/20/using-jekyll-asciidoctor-and-github-pages-for-static-site-creation/</id><content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>After I decided to start write things down, the first tool that I found for this task was Jekyll - a static site generator supported by GitHub Pages.
It was very useful for creating the first version of this blog, but finally, I decided to use Grain (hope to present it in the following article).
As a result of playing with Jekyll, in this article I will show how to build a simple blog using Jekyll as static site generator, GitHub Pages as static site server and Asciidoc as markdown language.
We will create a blog from scratch, add new posts and change default configuration and web pages layout using mentioned technologies.</p>
</div>
<!--more-->
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_why_static_matters">Why static matters?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The web started as a bunch of static sites that provided various pieces of useful information for first explorers of the internet.
But it turned into civilization phenomenon with exponential growth only when it became dynamic with all Web 2.0 stuff like social media, wikis, media platforms, etc.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Anyway, even today lots of web resources really need a very limited amount of dynamic magic.
If client state on your site is not persisted, it can be handled by JavaScript locally.
If content is changing relatively rarely, you can just redeploy it with every change.
If you need something like commenting feature, you can rely on external resources (for example <a href="https://disqus.com" target="_blank">disqus.com</a> in this case).</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And if you get rid of all heavy dynamic weapons like databases and server-side code and express your site as a collection of HMTL, CSS and JavaScript files you can gain some very worthy benefits.
The first and the main one is the ease of site deployment.
All you need to do is copy your files into any kind of web server (Apache, Nginx).
And if you go further and use cloud file storage (like S3) or dedicated web platform (like GitHub Pages), you get even more (think how it can help you in content management, content delivery, maintenance simplicity, performance, and security).</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_who_is_jekyll">Who is Jekyll?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="imageblock" style="text-align: right">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-ab698-ab69891f3e58371ac378b226143fa763.png" alt="jekyll ab698 ab69891f3e58371ac378b226143fa763">
</div>
<div class="title"><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strange_Case_of_Dr_Jekyll_and_Mr_Hyde" target="_blank">source</a></em></div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://jekyllrb.com" target="_blank">Jekyll</a> is a static site generator written in Ruby.
Actually what it does is taking your content along with the desired layout and transform them into a collection of HTML, CSS and JavaScript files ready for deployment and servicing as a static web resource.
Content can be provided in any form from plain text files or markdown to pieces of HTMLs.
The layout is specified as the name of one of the ready-to-go layouts Jekyll provides (with customization possibilities) or as your own HTML, CSS, and JavaScript files with template-related features.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-ecef3-ecef3ed5e49ee2c1093d722619911c85.png" alt="jekyll ecef3 ecef3ed5e49ee2c1093d722619911c85">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Moreover, Jekyll is a great example of the tool with both comprehensive predefined conventions and almost endless customization possibilities.
If all you need is a simple blog, you should just place you text-file posts named in a special way into the special directory, define few configuration parameters and you&#8217;re done.
If you need something more specific, you can include your own pieces of HTML, CSS or JavaScript anywhere you need, even using Jekyll as just template engine for your sources ignoring all other features.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_so_all_i_need_is_a_simple_blog">So, all I need is a simple blog</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Check <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/quickstart" target="_blank">Jekyll quick-start guide</a>!
You need to follow these 5 steps:</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p>Install <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/documentation/installation/" target="_blank">Ruby</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>gem install jekyll bundler</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>jekyll new myblog</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>cd myblog; bundle exec jekyll serve</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Go to <a href="http://localhost:4000" target="_blank">http://localhost:4000</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You should get result same as <a href="https://yermilov.github.io/jekyll-start/" target="_blank">this one</a>:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-707aa-707aab07625a4434b996c11a11c9a6ba.png" alt="jekyll 707aa 707aab07625a4434b996c11a11c9a6ba">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>However, you can do the same even without installing Ruby and Jekyll itself.
First, you need to fork repository or download sources from <a href="https://github.com/yermilov/mini-jekyll" target="_blank">mini-jekyll repository</a>, or, as an alternative, you can quickly create them by yourself:</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p>Create directory for your blog</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Create file _config.yml with the following content</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>


<div id="gistf25ae17a6bc85b7fc75eab310bc9ff52">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/f25ae17a6bc85b7fc75eab310bc9ff52.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic" start="3">
<li>
<p>Create file Gemfile with the following content</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>


<div id="gist118d18ea311905e224e311fd16f7c4dd">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/118d18ea311905e224e311fd16f7c4dd.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic" start="4">
<li>
<p>Create file index.md with the following content</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>


<div id="gist9cadf8cb8f96067e5022501ca825026a">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/9cadf8cb8f96067e5022501ca825026a.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic" start="5">
<li>
<p>Create file about.md with following content</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>


<div id="gist994c3dff2062a96f9f257000482e2c36">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/994c3dff2062a96f9f257000482e2c36.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic" start="6">
<li>
<p>Create file <span id="todayFileName">_posts/2017-02-20-welcome-to-mini-jekyll.md</span> with following content:</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>


<div id="gist8102dc4bee24aeef7f511d7211eaf741">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/8102dc4bee24aeef7f511d7211eaf741.js"></script>
</div>
<script>
  var today = new Date();
  var dd = today.getDate();
  var mm = today.getMonth() + 1; //January is 0!
  var yyyy = today.getFullYear();

  if (dd < 10) {
      dd = '0' + dd
  }

  if (mm < 10) {
      mm = '0' + mm
  }

  today = yyyy + '-' + mm + '-' + dd;

  document.getElementById('todayFileName').innerHTML = '_posts/' + today + '-welcome-to-mini-jekyll.md'
</script>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>How can you start this site without even installing Jekyll?
Easily, with support of <a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages</a> - web platform that serves static content from GitHub repositories.
Besides just showing content as it is, GitHub Pages can determine that your repository contains Jekyll project, render it and serve result.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-e5cd5-e5cd5a4b237fae4edc9efc449ec92f97.png" alt="jekyll e5cd5 e5cd5a4b237fae4edc9efc449ec92f97">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>All you need to do is:</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p><a href="https://github.com/new" target="_blank">Create new GitHub repository</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>git init</code> inside your local blog directory</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>git add .</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>git commit -m 'initial blog commit'</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>git remote add origin <a href="https://github.com/yermilov/mini-jekyll.git" class="bare">https://github.com/yermilov/mini-jekyll.git</a></code> (substitute URL with yours)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute <code>git push -u origin gh-pages</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Go to <a href="https://yermilov.github.io/mini-jekyll" target="_blank">https://yermilov.github.io/mini-jekyll</a> (substitute with your github username and repository name)</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-86b33-86b33272473f30136abb8f58bd27abcc.png" alt="jekyll 86b33 86b33272473f30136abb8f58bd27abcc">
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_got_jekyll_and_github_pages_what_s_about_asciidoctor">Got Jekyll and GitHub Pages. What&#8217;s about Asciidoctor?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If you want to create blog for simple text+images posts, you&#8217;ve already got a good starting point.
But if your blog is going to be developer-oriented, you probably may not be satisfied with using neither markdown nor HTML for your posts.
In this case, <a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/" target="_blank">Asciidoc</a> should be your default choice.
It shares the same concept as <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/" target="_blank">Markdown</a>, is partially compatible with it, but has much more powerful features needed for advanced drafting of articles, technical manuals, books, presentations, and prose.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org" target="_blank">Asciidoctor</a> is a toolchain that implements Asciidoc format.
We are going to integrate it with Jekyll for rendering content using <a href="https://github.com/asciidoctor/jekyll-asciidoc" target="_blank">jekyll-asciidoc plugin</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As a starting point, fork or download sources from <a href="https://github.com/asciidoctor/jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart" target="_blank">jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart repository</a>.
The same as before, instead you can download it and create your own repository from scratch with same content.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Unlike previous examples, some additional setup is needed.
GitHub Pages does not (yet) support rendering Asciidoc content, so you can&#8217;t just push it to GitHub repository and got rendered site back.
Luckily, there is an easy way to overcome this problem.
However, it will be great to show GitHub demand in Asciidoc rendering for example through <a href="http://github.com/support" target="_blank">GitHub support form</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-595ea-595eab93a79c0e1912251cdf8b32edbe.png" alt="jekyll 595ea 595eab93a79c0e1912251cdf8b32edbe">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Actually, we will setup <a href="https://travis-ci.org/" target="_blank">Travis CI server</a> to emulate GitHub Pages staging automation, and push blog live upon committing any change to the repository.
Steps to achieve it are perfectly described in <a href="https://github.com/asciidoctor/jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart/blob/master/README.adoc" target="_blank">jekyll-asciidoc plugin documentation</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-e1af1-e1af1db7acd5c92a9069103e2d6d7256.png" alt="jekyll e1af1 e1af1db7acd5c92a9069103e2d6d7256">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>After cloning quickstart repository you need to make two changes in the sources:</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p>Add GitHub personal access token (described <a href="https://github.com/asciidoctor/jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart/blob/master/README.adoc#6-encrypt-the-github-token-for-travis-ci" target="_blank">here</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Modify original <em>.Rakefile</em>, to make it possible to use your e-mail for automated pushes to your repository:</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>


<div id="gist4abe7931165f10cf28edd9b55c4d32ba">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/4abe7931165f10cf28edd9b55c4d32ba.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>After your push changes into <strong><strong>develop</strong></strong> branch (do not use <em>master</em> or <em>gh-pages</em> because it may cause conflicts), Travis CI automatically will pick up sources, render them using Jekyll and push them back into master or gh-pages branch (depending on GitHub conventions).</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now you can go to <a href="https://yermilov.github.io/jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart" target="_blank">https://yermilov.github.io/jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart</a> (substitute with your github username and repository name) and enjoy!</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-e7f2b-e7f2bd8762f464e3fe2a7f2f3acb50a8.png" alt="jekyll e7f2b e7f2bd8762f464e3fe2a7f2f3acb50a8">
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_adding_new_post">Adding new post</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The first thing you probably want to do with your blog is to create a new post.
To do it, add file named <em>yyyy-mm-dd-new-post.adoc</em> (substitute yyyy-mm-dd with publication date and new-post with short post name) with following content:</p>
</div>


<div id="gista7a48ff65668b4299bf5f9692b4a9c46">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/a7a48ff65668b4299bf5f9692b4a9c46.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-c5427-c5427c7c2496d42ac1d8b6ff61414a0e.png" alt="jekyll c5427 c5427c7c2496d42ac1d8b6ff61414a0e">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>For quick start with Asciidoc refer to <a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-writers-guide/" target="_blank">Writer&#8217;s Guide</a>.
After it, you can proceed with more advanced <a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-syntax-quick-reference/" target="_blank">Syntax Quick Reference</a> and full <a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/user-manual/" target="_blank">User Manual</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Probably, you already have some post on external resources you want to link to your new blog.
With Jekyll&#8217;s flexibility, this is the matter of two easy steps.
First of all, create file that will contain your external post metadata.
Name it <em>yyyy-mm-dd-external-post.<strong>md</strong></em> similarly to regular posts.</p>
</div>


<div id="gist7889355953f8277594ca2f2a8c57215f">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/7889355953f8277594ca2f2a8c57215f.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>After it, open file <em><em>_layouts/default.html</em></em> and do following changes:</p>
</div>


<div id="gista158df94b32e91588acdaf7fb073d629">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/a158df94b32e91588acdaf7fb073d629.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now link in the posts feed is pointing to original external link.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_improving_pages_layout">Improving pages layout</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-33bb0-33bb0628a770179921350f59ae06896b.png" alt="jekyll 33bb0 33bb0628a770179921350f59ae06896b">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As we have already made a minor change to default page layout in our blog, let&#8217;s try some more significant ones, like changing pages layout.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>For the starting point, pages layout is pretty straightforward.
There is a file named <em>default.html</em> in the <em><em>_layouts</em></em> folder and it&#8217;s used for all site pages.
Each page (<em>index.adoc</em> or any from the <em><em>_posts</em></em> folder) during rendering is placed instead of <code>{{ content }}</code> placeholder.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-5de01-5de01f5a2d2a2f8b4e4a68955562eef1.png" alt="jekyll 5de01 5de01f5a2d2a2f8b4e4a68955562eef1">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Let&#8217;s now split it to different layouts.
First, to change home page layout, create file <em>_layouts/home.html</em>:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistf8e11c33860336e880f774d232ec0508">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/f8e11c33860336e880f774d232ec0508.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>First 3 lines are YAML configuration of the layout.
Here we specify that we want to inherit default layout, which implies placing content of current page instead of <code>{{ content }}</code> placeholder.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now, create file <em>_layouts/post.html</em>. It will be used as layout for all post pages.</p>
</div>


<div id="gist992833bd62105b491f5ba7ee2fa93b9d">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/992833bd62105b491f5ba7ee2fa93b9d.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Next, modify <em>_layouts/default.html</em>. Do the following change:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistf78b89670d5da8f3e57a5941c7c33b34">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/f78b89670d5da8f3e57a5941c7c33b34.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>After finishing with layout, we need to reconfigure content files.
Let&#8217;s start from <em>index.adoc</em>.
Now it can be just:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistc9ab333a1f1318837bc82885e9cdf9bc">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/c9ab333a1f1318837bc82885e9cdf9bc.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Proceed with post files.
Regular post should look like:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist08ed4a66561c14bb8809450f09be9cfb">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/08ed4a66561c14bb8809450f09be9cfb.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>External post metadata should look like:</p>
</div>


<div id="gistff4701d26a3d727df1fa91d1c17d2e23">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/ff4701d26a3d727df1fa91d1c17d2e23.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The last thing we should do in scope of this post is organizing our layout a little bit.
For now, our default layout is quite big, let&#8217;s split it with help of include feature.
As example, we will take page footer.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-faaab-faaabca1ee1e62db70a6b4c9409660d5.png" alt="jekyll faaab faaabca1ee1e62db70a6b4c9409660d5">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>First, create file <em>_includes/footer.html</em> with following content:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist52ae2b49bb67c02b38e04cd0a83cea72">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/52ae2b49bb67c02b38e04cd0a83cea72.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Next, do the following change with <em>_layouts/default.html</em>:</p>
</div>


<div id="gist16edd990579e2f562ecbff880e5dc0b6">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/16edd990579e2f562ecbff880e5dc0b6.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You can notice, that footer uses variables named starting with <code>site.</code>.
They are taken from <em>_config.yml</em> file.
Add two lines to it (substitute with your personal data):</p>
</div>


<div id="gist80964004f7c01b96fd47d2120e09a751">
  <script src="https://gist.github.com/80964004f7c01b96fd47d2120e09a751.js"></script>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now we are done!
Let&#8217;s examine final result:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock" style="text-align: right">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-350da-350da985b22ab2d3d61f647f644be394.png" alt="jekyll 350da 350da985b22ab2d3d61f647f644be394">
</div>
<div class="title"><em>Home page</em></div>
</div>
<div class="imageblock" style="text-align: right">
<div class="content">
<img src="/images/2017-02-20-jekyll-githubpages-asciidoc/jekyll-366e7-366e77e92daa91ca729cf28a15b3acf5.png" alt="jekyll 366e7 366e77e92daa91ca729cf28a15b3acf5">
</div>
<div class="title"><em>Post page</em></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_links">Links</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://jekyllrb.com" target="_blank">Jekyll home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://github.com/yermilov/mini-jekyll" target="_blank">Mini-Jekyll repository</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/" target="_blank">Markdown home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org" target="_blank">Asciidoctor home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/" target="_blank">What is Asciidoc?</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-writers-guide/" target="_blank">Asciidoc Writer&#8217;s Guide</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-syntax-quick-reference/" target="_blank">Asciidoc Syntax Quick Reference</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/user-manual/" target="_blank">Asciidoctor User Manual</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://github.com/asciidoctor/jekyll-asciidoc" target="_blank">jekyll-asciidoc plugin home</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://github.com/asciidoctor/jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart" target="_blank">jekyll-asciidoc-quickstart repository</a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></content></entry></feed>